<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A lasting ievvell, for religious woemen In the summe of a sermon, preached at the funerall of mistris Mary Crosse, late wife of Mr. Henry Crosse of Barnestaple in the countie of Deuon merchant, Nouemb. 11. 1628. and now published with some additions. With a briefe description of her life and death. By William Crompton, preacher of the Word of God at Barnestaple in Deuon.</title>
            <author>Crompton, William, 1599?-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19624</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6058</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117122</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852337</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852337</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17653</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19624)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17653)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1134:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A lasting ievvell, for religious woemen In the summe of a sermon, preached at the funerall of mistris Mary Crosse, late wife of Mr. Henry Crosse of Barnestaple in the countie of Deuon merchant, Nouemb. 11. 1628. and now published with some additions. With a briefe description of her life and death. By William Crompton, preacher of the Word of God at Barnestaple in Deuon.</title>
                  <author>Crompton, William, 1599?-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[42] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. Stansby] for Edvvard Blount,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-F⁴ (-F4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Crosse, Mary, d. 1628 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17653:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17653:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LASTING IEWELL, <hi>FOR</hi> RELIGIOVS WOEMEN.</p>
            <p>In the ſumme of a Sermon, Preached at the Funerall of Miſtris MARY CROSSE, late Wife of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. HENRY CROSSE of <hi>Barne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaple</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Deuon</hi> Merchant, <hi>Nouemb.</hi> 11. 1628. and now publiſhed with ſome Additions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a briefe deſcription of her life and death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By WILLIAM CROMPTON, Preacher of the Word of God at <hi>Barneſtaple</hi> in <hi>Deuon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus ſhall it be done to them whom the Lord will honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for EDVVARD BLOVNT. 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17653:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17653:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL CHRISTOPHER BLACKHALL Eſquire, and to the vertuous Gentle-woman, Miſtris DOROTHIE BLACKHALL, his Wife, <hi>Grace, Mercy, and Peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orſhipfull Sir, my loſſe hath occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned this gaine to the Church, the death of my deareſt friend gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing life to this Monument: <hi>Iacob</hi> erects a Pillar vpon the Graue of his beloued <hi>Rachell, Gen. 35.20.</hi> my deſire was, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of mine might not periſh; nor her Vertues with her body, be buried in the Land, where all things are forgotten: for that end I haue at length preuailed to make that publike, which was deliuered vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſhort warning (the ſpeaker limited both for time and Text) at her funerall: neither knew I any to whom I might more fitly Dedicate the ſame (of right belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to her neereſt Kinſman) then to your ſelfe, with your vertuous ſecond: deare ſhee was vnto you, while
<pb facs="tcp:17653:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> liuing, and I know the fragrant ſmell of a bruiſed roſe, will not be vnwelcome, though dead. I could not then wiſh her to liue ſtill in miſery; I now deſire ſhee may liue in memory; according to the promiſe of God, made vnto his Saints; <hi>Pſal. 112.6. Prou. 10.7. The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the iuſt is bleſſed; and the righteous ſhall be had in euerlaſting remembrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Worthy Sir, if you may hereby reape any comfort, I ſhall haue the more content; if God may haue any glory, the Church any benefite, religious Woemen en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement hence, the Author, I know, obtaines his expected reward: who otherwiſe was vnwilling to feele againe the laſhes of this cenſuring Age. Thus, not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to finde a kinde acceptance of a good meaning; I commit all to the bleſſing of God, leauing you and yours to the rich mercies of God our Father in Chriſt, and reſt now as euer,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Barum, <date>
                     <hi>this 14.</hi> Nouemb. <hi>1629.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips Kinſman to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, in what I am able, HENRY CROSSE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:17653:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Laſting Ievvell, FOR RELIGIOVS <hi>WOEMEN.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 31.30.31.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Fauour is deceitfull, and Beautie, vanitie; but a woman that feareth the Lord, ſhe ſhall be prayſed; giue her of the fruit of her hands, and let her owne workes prayſe her in the gates.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His portion of Scripture, Right Worſhipfull, Men, Fathers, and Brethren (all dearely beloued) in the beſt beloued Chriſt Ieſus, is part of a Prophecie, ſee the firſt verſe of the Chapter, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore certaine;<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.19.</note> S. <hi>Peter</hi> cals it the ſure word of propheſie, which came not by the will of man, but men of God ſpake as they were mooued by the holy Ghoſt. S. <hi>Paul</hi> chargeth vs that
<pb facs="tcp:17653:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> we deſpiſe not prophecying: either by vnbeliefe, or by an idle, fruitleſſe hearing; a long <hi>Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rdium</hi> to prepare you. I ſhall not (and haue good reaſon to hope) I need not vſe, hauing hitherto, found you as louing, willing, and attentiue hearers, as euer I ſpake vnto (God grant continuance with increaſe of practice) where attention will proue obedience to our Sauiour, and obedience bring profit with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, the matter carries its owne weight to procure entrance into the dulleſt eare; onely take heed how you heare this Prophecie which <hi>Salomon</hi> learned of his mother.</p>
            <p>In the whole Chapter, you haue firſt generall directions for a good King, and in him, for any that truely feare God, and deſire to order their life ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his word; and they are eſpecially three, conteined in the nine firſt verſes: Firſt to deale iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with euery one;<note place="margin">Verſe 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>Giue vnto God the things that are Gods;</hi> honour, glory, with vniuerſall obedience; giue vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and with him to euery other man, what belongs vnto them,<note place="margin">Iuſtice firſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, becauſe firſt in being and chiefe in working.</note> by the Law of Nature, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, rayſe not your ſelues vpon the ruine of your brethren, vniuſt increaſe will conſume the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall: yet looke not ſo much vpon others, as to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get your ſelues; Iuſtice like Charitie muſt begin at home; he cannot be acceptably iuſt towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the acts of commutatiue, and diſtributiue Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; who is cruelly vniuſt to himſelfe in neglecting the ſafety of his owne ſoule: defraud not your owne ſoules of ſpirituall food and tillage; to ſtarue, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them grow needy; is the greateſt Iniuſtice; ſowe the ſeedes of grace, your ſoules require it, and
<pb facs="tcp:17653:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> you ſhall reape the harueſt of glory; your Sauiour hath promiſed it.</p>
            <p>Secondly to bee temperate in the vſe of wine,<note place="margin">Verſe 4.5.6. Sobriety.</note> and ſtrong drinke; God commands it, nature requires it, common honeſty cals for it; a cuſtomary drunkard, (whether by quaffing, or ſlipping in paſſiue or actiue drunkenneſſe, glorying in that ſhamefull practice, to lay others aſleep) Tauerne-haunter, health-drinker, and deſtroyer, fights againſt all; giant-like in his <hi>alie. Metamorphoſis,</hi> thinkes himſelfe able to wage warre with nature, procures ſuch a habit in it, as will not be remooued without great difficulty, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets God, his ſeruice, himſelfe, wife, Children, ſoule and all: let all ſtarue for bread, ſoe hee may haue drinke enough; makes himſelfe vnſeruiceable, and conſequently a ſlaggering burthen, both to Church and Common-wealth, layeth himſelfe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly open to the fierce wrath of God Almightie, to all the danger and diſgrace can poſſibly bee thought on: as by many wofull examples we haue ſeene in euery age: and finally looſeth all his friends, good name, eſtate, health, and ſaluation, without ſpeedy, and ſpeciall repentance: read at your lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.37, 38. <hi>Prou.</hi> 33.19.20, 21, 29. <hi>Prou.</hi> 30.31, 32, 33. <hi>Eſay</hi> 5.22. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5 21. then conſider how vile a vice drunkenneſſe is, and how hard to be left.<note place="margin">Chaſtitie. This is firſt in intention, laſt in expreſſion, as the ſubiect of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe required.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, to be reſolute in reſiſting all the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full baytes of feminine beauty; vnruly appetite, would betray our ſtrength, and make vs yeeld at the ſight of euery weake woman; did we not heare ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther voyce from heauen, Giue not your ſtrength to
<pb facs="tcp:17653:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> woemen, nor your wayes to that which deſtroyeth Kings. It is reported that <hi>Alexander</hi> would not looke on the wife of <hi>Darius,</hi> leaſt hee that had ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come many men ſhould be ſhamefully vanquiſhed by one woeman; one wanton eye may let in more ruines to the ſoule, then two hands can thruſt out: gaze not on beautie, it is vanitie; liſten not to the voice of fauour, it is deceitfull; let not your hearts be inſnared with ſuch knowne traps; the gaine of the fleſh, is in this ſenſe the loſſe of the ſoule: reade what is written:<note place="margin">Prou. 2.18, 19.</note> The houſe of a whoriſh woeman inclines vnto death, and her pathes vnto the dead: None that go vnto her; returne againe, neither take they hold of the pathes of life. She hath caſt downe many wounded, ſtrong men haue beene ſlaine by her, her houſe is the way to Hell, going downe to the Chambers of death.<note place="margin">Prou. 7.26.27.</note> When the Foxe ſaw many going, none returning from the Lions denne, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to goe for feare of like danger: Let vs hence learne to be wiſe,<note place="margin">Foelix quem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt, aliena pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricula cautum.</note> leaſt wee complaine too late. How haue wee hated inſtruction, and deſpiſed reproofe? how haue we diſobeyed the voice of our teachers? and refuſed to incline our eare to them that inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vs?</p>
            <p>Secondly, wee haue in this Chapter an exact de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, and Commendation of a vertuous woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, beginning at the tenth verſe: which I would commend to all that are, or deſire to be good wiues: that you would peruſe it once a weeke; not omitting ſet Tymes, for reading other parts of holy writ: my Text is the concluſion of it, wherein you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue with me,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:17653:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>1. The fading Condition of outward endowments compriſed in,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fauour is deceitfull, and</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Beautie vanitie.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The laſting worth and dignity of inward grace, contained in,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But a Woman that feareth the Lord ſhee ſhall bee prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The dutie of all men, towards vertuous women, Expreſt in the laſt words,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Giue her the fruite of her hands, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein I ſhall briefly touch theſe particulars:
<list>
                  <item>1. Who they are muſt be praiſed,
<list>
                        <item>Woemen.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. For what?
<list>
                        <item>The feare of the Lord.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. How they muſt be praiſed.
<list>
                        <item>By the fruit of their hands, and their owne worthes.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. By whom?
<list>
                        <item>By their Children, Husbands, Neighbours; all are enioined to giue good woemen their due praiſe.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Of all which in their order, and firſt by way of Explication.</p>
            <p>The cenſure of Nature and naturall endowments,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fauour is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fauour,</hi> may be taken 2. wayes: firſt, for inward affection, which is a motion of the mind, ſtirred vp by the apprehenſion of ſome excellencie in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie fauoured, as when wee ſay this, or that great man fauours vs, ſmiles vpon vs, loues vs entirely: then
<pb facs="tcp:17653:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> this fauour what more deceitfull? who can tell when hee hath it? or diſcouer a falſe heart vnder a flattering forehead? did not <hi>Cain</hi> commune with his brother, whom he meant to kill? was not <hi>Ioabs</hi> ſpeech peaceable, when his purpoſe was to ſmite <hi>Abner?</hi> how ſweet were his words to innocent <hi>Amaſa?</hi> Art thou in health my Brother? when a ſword was in his hand to free him from all diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes? <hi>Abſalon</hi> inuites his brother <hi>Ammon,</hi> to feaſt with him, but the gueſt muſt be ſlaughtered by him: <hi>Iudas</hi> cries haile Maſter, when he came to betray the ſonne of man with a kiſſe: What apiſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, bowing, becking, ſcraping, the fooliſh froth of feigned loue, doe we behold amongſt men? while there is no correſpondencie betweene the heart and the hand? what promiſes haue wee had? what proteſtations haue wee heard? which haue proued abortiues, liuing and dying in the ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: who relyes thereon in theſe daies, builds on ſandy ground. Beleeue them that ſpeake out of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; truſt not fauour, it is deceitfull: ſo true is that of the Pſalmiſt, mens words may be ſmoother then oyle, when there is no truth in the inward parts: Or ſuppoſe one to haue it; who can tell how long he ſhall enioy it? health, and ſickneſſe, life and death, ſun-ſhine and ſtormes, day and night change not ſo often, as this deceitfull fauour; to day wee may heare <hi>Iacobs</hi> voice, to morrow feele <hi>Eſaus</hi> hands; the leaſt error, rumor, or conceit of one, cruſhes this affection: rich words with an ayery iſſue, proclaimes the Parents folly. This fauour of wicked men and women, is nothing worth: like
<pb facs="tcp:17653:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſmoake to the eyes; or the reede of Egypt to the hand: what extremity of folly driues worldly Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lititians then, or boone companions and good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes (as they are tearmed) to preferre it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fauour of God, to ſeeke more greedily for it then reconciliation with God in the blood of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>The fauour of great men may be ſought, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, good vſe made of it, yet one dram of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour in Chriſt is more worth then the fauour of all the Princes in the World. Let mee be Gods fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, I care not whether the World ſmile or frowne; let others purſue this deceitfull fauour; but Lord, doe thou lift vp the light of thy countenance vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, fauour may be taken for outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, in bodie, and face; ioyned with a iuſtly tempered complexion; when all the humours ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt an equall power, without any ſelfe-ruining de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of dominion: this is the fauour here meant, and is deceitfull two wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt actiuely, when it deceiues others, and that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in regard of iudgement, when men thinke woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to be ſuch as they ſeeme to be, perfect for parts, beautifull, healthie, ſober, chaſte, temperate; there being indeede and truth not any one, but the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of theſe qualities in them: or in regard of loue, and liking, when men ſuffer themſelues to bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared with the very outward fauour; making Senſe the guide vnto reaſon, and beautie the ground of their affection:<note place="margin">Gen. 6.2.34.2.</note> ſo were the ſonnes of God deceiued in the old world; <hi>Sechem,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Hamor,
<pb facs="tcp:17653:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> Sampſon</hi> with <hi>Dalilah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 16. 2. Sam. 11.2.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> with <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> and many more in euery age: few eyes that haue not thus beene foyled; looking through theſe deceitfull ſpectacles, haue beene miſtaken in their obiect. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath taught vs to tell you this, fauour is deceitfull; and leaſt it ſhould not be enough deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of it ſelfe: there are certaine appurtenances which make it more deceitfull, as painting, perewigs, falſe eyes, arteficiall teeth, cawles of net-worke to catch wantons; round tyers, chaines, bracelets, mufflers, rings, earrings, with the reſt of that ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robe ſet open by the Prophet:<note place="margin">Eſay 3.19.20.21.22.23.</note> gaze not on this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, faire and louely it appeares; but defiles the heart, leaues a ſtaine vpon the Soule, and is it not deceitfull?</p>
            <p>Secondly, paſſiuely, deceiuing it ſelfe; promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing conſtancie, when nothing is more fraile; ſee if it euer could indure the ſhining of the Sun, blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the wind, falling of the raine, the leaſt inward griefe; two or three fits of an Ague, the ſmall pocks, bearing of Children, conſume and leaue it no place; this day it lookes as if it would bee alwayes ſoe; to morrow, as if it had neuer beene ſo; and is it not deceitfull? a meanes it is to coozen many of the foode of life. They cannot goe to Church in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer for heate, nor in winter for cold, it will ſpoile their complexion; and is it not deceitfull? what meane the multitude of vailes and maskes, the cloſer you keepe it, the leſſer while it will laſt, and is it not deceitfull?</p>
            <p>Beautie is vanitie: here wee haue a more liuely expreſſion of the former: I know no great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb facs="tcp:17653:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> betweene fauour and beauty: in our ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpeech they are often put one for another: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this fauour is refer'd to proportion, beautie to complexion: though in ſtrictneſſe of ſpeech, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie being ſomething ariſing from both.</p>
            <p>Beautie is twofold. 1. Inward of the heart and mind mentioned. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.2.<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.2. Cant. 5.10.6, 4. Geneſ. 29.17, 12, 11.26.7. Eſter 1.11. Geneſ. 39.6. 1. Sam. 16.12.25, 3. 2. Sam. 13.25.11, 2.</note> This is true ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall beauty; not here meant. Another there is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the face and countenance; ariſing from a pure mixture, and quicke motion of the humours: as in Scripture we read often of ſuch beautie; high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be Commended when it meets with a gracious heart: in <hi>Rachel, Sarah, Rebecka, Vaiſthi, Ioſeph, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Abigail, Abſalon, Bathſheba</hi> with many others: giuen to good ones, leſt it ſhould be thought euill: giuen to the wicked, leſt it ſhould be eſteem'd more then is meete: yet in both it is truely ſaid to be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie; vnprofitable and ſoone fading, like ſome pleaſant flower, that ſtoopes to the firſt ſharpe blaſt: Beautie and vanitie may be compared to <hi>Zacheries</hi> two ſtaues, one is no ſooner broken,<note place="margin">Zach. 11.7.</note> but the other ſucceedes.</p>
            <p>The prayſe of grace and gracious Actions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But a woman that feareth the Lord.</hi> What woman ſoeuer, young or old, maid or wife, that feares the Lord: not with a ſlauiſh feare, that may be in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels and Reprobates which is to feare with ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred; nor with a ſeruile feare onely,<note place="margin">Acts 10.34, 35.</note> though it bee commendable, and in ſome ſort neceſſary:<note place="margin">Betweene ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile feare there is a graduall if no ſpecificall difference.</note> but with a filiall feare, ioyned, with a heartie loue of him ſo feared: ſhee that is godly and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous makes conſcience of her wayes, hates euery
<pb facs="tcp:17653:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> knowne ſinne, delights in the ſocietie of Gods Saints on earth; vſes Gods ordinances in their ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, performes that office her place requires out of faith and obedience vnto God; ſuch a one ſhall bee praiſed: Faire ones may be fauoured of ſome for a time; good ones ſhall be fauoured of all for euer; grace brings true honour; no glory without it; her husband ſhall praiſe her, and bleſſe God he euer ſaw her: her Children ſhall riſe vp in token of her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and call her bleſſed; becauſe fruitfull; bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Chriſt in her heart, them in her wombe.</p>
            <p>A good woeman was neuer barren; ſhee cannot but bee a mother of many Children, in one ſenſe or other: her comforts and leſſons, workes of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie and charity, her ſpeech and behauiour: what are they all but ſo many iſſues of grace? Praiſed ſhall ſhe be of God, his word and ſeruants, had in honour of all that are round about her (if men were ſilent, the ſtones would cry out) and her good name ſhall remaine for euer.</p>
            <p>Leaſt a good action ſhould miſcarry in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the holy Ghoſt in the laſt clauſe of this booke and Chapter deſcribes how ſhe muſt be praiſed:</p>
            <p>By the fruit of her hands, by her owne workes:</p>
            <p>The hands of a gracious woman walke faſter then her tongue, the tongue is not idle, nor ill employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; exerciſed often in the prayſes of her God: giue her the reward of her hands, not withholding the fruit of her lips.</p>
            <p>The fruit of the hands, growes on three branches; in feruent praying; diligent working: charitable giuing: the firſt lookes vnto God; the ſecond to her
<pb facs="tcp:17653:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> houſe and familie; the laſt to the poore and needy: her owne workes they are called, becauſe done by her ſelfe; enabled with Gods grace, during life.</p>
            <p>Let others build Trophes to preſerue their memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, after death: a godly woman erects alaſting mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument with her own hands: whence we may note by the way; firſt, that it is one propertie of the feare of God to make woemen fruitfull in euery good, both of nature and grace; the want of this makes barren in each degree. Secondly, that works of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, truely praiſe-worthie, ſhould be done during life; let her owne works praiſe her; not the works of others, though done by her appointment.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to detaine the iuſt reward of praiſe from ſuch good woemen, is iniuſtice: giue them the fruit of their hands: let ſuch wiues freely inioy the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of their owne labour; let them ſit vnder the vines of their owne planting, and weare the cloath of their owne making; Let husbands neither reſtraine, nor ſuſpect ſuch as feare God; either they doe not euill, or would not doe it; the will muſt be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the deede: let their large prouiſion and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple portion, publiſh their iuſt demerit in all aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies; it is the greateſt pitie and iniuſtice that men ſhould ſuffer vertuous woemen to want competent maintenance; incouragement, by due praiſe, and commendation; he may be puniſht with a bad wife, that deales vnkindly with a good one.</p>
            <p>Concluſions, or obſeruations doctrinall hence na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ariſing for our inſtruction are three.</p>
            <p>Firſt that fauour and beauty, as formerly deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, are vanitie; a ſeemely proportion with the
<pb facs="tcp:17653:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> beſt complection, is but a ſandy foundation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to build our affection; whether we conſider de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, or praiſe; Beautie alone is like a pleaſant baite with a poyſoned hooke, to catch and gall vs, not to feed and comfort vs; neither for this can any merit praiſe: For firſt it is the worke and gift of God; not to vs, but to him eſpecially appertains the praiſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is a thing common to good and bad: the worſt women haue often the greateſt ſhare: moſt beautie, leaſt grace; they dote ſo much of what they haue, as that they neuer thinke of what they want; as alſo with reaſonable and vnreaſonable Creatures: how farre doe ſome flowers exceed the faireſt face.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, beautie alone is very vnſeemely; like a gold ring in a Swines ſnout, ſo (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) is a faire woeman without diſcretion.<note place="margin">Prou. 11.12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is deceitfull, both actiuely, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely: beſides, beautie and fauour in their beſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell; are but ſhadowes of Good comparatiuely; as may be gathered from diuers paſſages of the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher; and therefore none ſhould rely on them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther owners, or beholders: Firſt, becauſe they are not laſting, as hath beene noted in the expoſition; that cannot make man happie, which is capable of not-being: ſecondly, they can giue no ſatisfying content, while they doe laſt: beautie and fauour fill not the heart, though obtained: the eye is not ſatisfied with ſeeing;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.8. Prou. 27.20.</note> that which hath power to ſtay and ſatisfie the mind of man, is ſimply one; affect beautie, we cannot wantonly and meerely for it ſelfe without deſire of change; now this pleaſes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:17653:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> that: delight in variety is the companion of luſt; neither of which can ſtand together with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this may ſerue for inſtructiue informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to men and woemen. Firſt, let faire woemen learne hence to eſteeme ſo of their beautie; bee not miſtaken in your face; if you haue nothing better, you are but as painted Sepulchres; your outward ſtructure couers a maſſe of foule Corruption: a flower may be wondrous faire to looke vpon, yet wee ſay it is but a flower, and accordingly to bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed: ſo beautie, though iuſtly admired, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in ſome part the excellence of the workeman; yet <hi>Salomon</hi> tels vs, it is but vanitie, compared to the beauty of the inner man: nay, what is more vgly then a faire face, with a foule, proud, luſtful heart? the fairer any are, the more carefull ſhould they be; not to offend by it, themſelues or others, and the more thankfull for it, many good things of nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more ſeruice to glorifie the author thereof: beauty with grace, a faire face with an humble holy heart, are Iewels of ineſtimable worth. Did faire woemen know how highly outward beauty is ſet forth by the preſence of inward grace,<note place="margin">Gratior eſt pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chro, &amp;c.</note> they would ſtriue for it, and ſeeke each to exceed other. Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie without grace, is one of Sathans ſnares to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap poſſeſſors and paſſengers both at once.</p>
            <p>Secondly, men may hence learne wiſedome in two reſpects. Firſt to recall this truth into minde, when they are tempted with beautie; ſhall we truſt what is knowne to bee deceitfull? Secondly, that they doe not ſo much delight in, and admire it, as to
<pb facs="tcp:17653:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> make it the chiefeſt motiue, or ground worke of their loue and liking, hee is accounted in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of wiſedome a fooliſh man that builds on a ſandie foundation;<note place="margin">Math. 7.26.</note> eſpecially conſidering the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing danger. For firſt, Stories tell vs that many great ones haue falne hereby:<note place="margin">Prou. 6.25.7.26.</note> other mens harmes ſhould make vs the more wary, principall pillars in Iſraell, <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> father and ſonne were foulely ſhaken; what may weake ones feare? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, beſides the diſcord hath beene rayſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Brethren; warre proclaimed, blood ſhed, onely about this deceitfull beautie: the practice of <hi>Paris</hi> may at any time bring Grecians to the walles of <hi>Troy.</hi> Thirdly, and after all, ſuppoſe it peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly obtained, when outward fauour decaies, that loue grounded firſt thereon will decay alſo, if no further hurt enſue. It is reported of <hi>Helen,</hi> or ſome other of her complexion, that on a time, after ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, viewing her ſelfe in a glaſſe, and ſeeing her beautie decayed, ſuddainly fell into a relapſe, and through the malignitie of a ſtrong conceit dyed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this cenſures and condemnes the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of many amongſt vs, both men and woemen; woemen, who hauing and ſeeking nothing elſe but fauour and beautie, beſtow all, or moſt part of their time about it, curling and cutting the haire, pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, pinning, lacing, dreſſing, adorning, &amp;c. it argues great lightneſſe, and want of the loue of grace, to toyle ſo about a knowne vanitie: how light then many of our Engliſh Dames are, their practice ſhewes, looking more on the Glaſſe then on the Bible: being more carefull of their faces,
<pb facs="tcp:17653:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> then their hearts: pitty it is faire Creatures ſhould ſo befoole themſelues, onely with a meere out-ſide of good.</p>
            <p>Men that are carried away moſt with beauty, let them learne to ſee, and acknowledge their youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full error, as they deſire to be ſaued: are not you one cauſe of their miſery? offences may come; but woe to them by whom they come. I ſee not how it can be auoyded: for, did not woemen by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſee, men preferring outward endowments to inward graces, we ſhould quickly finde a generall change; woemen would ſtriue to be good, did they ſee men affect goodneſſe: it is ordinary policie to vſe that baite which the fiſh moſt delight to play with: in this worſt age of ours, what is moſt looked after in woemen but beautie, riches, or both? are they rich, beautifull, of rich parentage; is there any hope of preferment by them in the world? (Religion the chiefeſt linke between man and wife) grace and a vertuous education is little reſpected: this makes woemen admire the one, as their chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt good, neglect the other, as little worth: Let ſuch men know, a day will come, when they ſhall confeſſe, and bewayle this pleaſing and ſelfe-decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing error; if they bee not arraigned as guiltie in part of Female folly.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, here is comfort for ſuch as ſettle their affection on better ground, vpon the image of Chriſt, and the graces of the ſpirit, ſhining in the partie affected: this Foundation is rockie, durable: the proportion will neuer change, nor the beautie decay, the gates of hell ſhall neuer preuaile againſt it;
<pb facs="tcp:17653:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> by vſe it increaſes, and out-liues the nipping blaſts of all-conſuming time: fauour is deceitfull, and beautie is vanitie: why ſhould any bee proud that haue it, or grieue that want it? a wrinckled fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, ſwarthy complexion, a perſon in bodie or in face any wayes deformed; with a vertuous, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious mind, appeares more beautifull to the eye of iudgement, then the faireſt Creature in the world: Not ſo, ſince <hi>Eue</hi> aſſented to the craftie Serpent, none of her poſterity appeare beautifull; but ſuch as are dipt in the blood of Chriſt, and cloathed with his righteouſneſſe: For the cenſure of ſome ſcorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully fooliſh in bewraying their owne ignorance; paſſe it ouer, it cannot harme you; a good ſoule ſhall not be denyed entrance into heauen for want of beautie.</p>
            <p>Let me therefore exhort you (my dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Lord, men and woemen) affect not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, it is deceitfull; dote not on beautie, it is vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. To Profeſſors of Chriſts Goſpell I ſpeake; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion not your ſelues to this world, miſpend not precious time in pampring foode for wormes; the greateſt gallant, and faireſt face, ſhall ſtoope ere long to lodge in clay: beleeue it now, or elſe you will one day find it ſo, when it is too late: build not your affection on ſuch a ſandie foundation, the ſturdie windes will ruinate whatſoeuer you erect thereon: <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpake out of experience deare bought; you haue wiſedome offered you at a cheape rate, and it may be as good as that which is further fetcht; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne, nor flight it not; Conſider what is truth, and the Lord bleſſe it vnto you.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17653:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Secondly, in that the feare of the Lord is here oppoſed to fauour and beautie, and by oppoſition preferd; we learne, that the feare of the Lord with good workes, are woemens chiefeſt Iewels, things of greateſt worth.</p>
            <p>I ioyne theſe two, becauſe they cannot well be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated; no filiall feare of God without good workes; no good workes without the feare of the Lord: theſe are wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mens chiefeſt Iewels, and of greateſt worth; in regard they laſt longeſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them beſt, yeelding certaine comfort, with a free reward: that ſoule which once feeles the benefit, will not part with it for all the world. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is euery where full to this purpoſe;<note place="margin">Pſal. 19 9, Eſa. 33.6. Prouer. 11.16.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>the feare of the Lord is excellent, and endures for euer; the feare of the Lord is a treaſure; a gracious woman retaines true honour, better is a little with the feare of the Lord, then great treaſure:</hi> better is a little beautie with the feare of the Lord, nay fairer is the fouleſt face, with inward grace, then <hi>Helens</hi> beautie, with a proud, wan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ton luxurious mind:<note place="margin">Prou. 31.10.</note> who can find a vertuous woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? her price is farre aboue rubies: therefore it is the Apoſtles aduice, that woemen ſhould array themſelues in comely apparell, with ſhamefaſtneſſe, and modeſty, not with broydered haire, gold, pearles, or coſtly apparell: (no better ornament for a woeman, then an humble mind) no richer pearle then a pure heart) but as becommeth woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that profeſſe the feare of God,<note place="margin">1. Timo. 2.9.10.</note> with good workes; ſeconded by his partner in labour,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.4.</note> whoſe adorning (ſpeaking of good woemen) let it not be that outward, of plaiting the hayre, wearing of
<pb facs="tcp:17653:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> gold, or putting on of apparell: but let it be the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en man of the heart, in that which is not corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, euen the ornament of a meeke and quiet ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which is in the ſight of God of great price.</p>
            <p>Let common woemen gull themſelues and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, with paynted ſhewes, euery vertuous ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron knowes good workes to be a better ornament then cut or plaited haire, pearles, gold, or coſtly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray: many ſimple ones, either know not, or beleeue not this, obſerue them ſtrutting with their ſpangled foreheads, as peacocks vſe to doe with their tailes, haue nothing to glory in but what is borrowed from the Creature, wanting the chiefeſt Iewell, all the reſt are as filthy rags.</p>
            <p>This truth will further appeare vnto vs, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider firſt that which the Scripture ſpeakes of, the feare of the Lord in thoſe ſeuerall places cited,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.9. Prou. 1.7.10, 27, 14, 27. Math. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. 1. Tim. 4.8.6.6. Philip. 4.11.</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may eaſily diſcerne the excellencie of it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that ſweet contentation of mind, with our portion allotted, as with what wee are and haue; beautifull, or deformed, riches or pouertie; which followes as an effect of this feare; it hath the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of this life and that to come: Godlines with contentment is great gaine: heereby was S. <hi>Paul</hi> taught, in what eſtate ſoeuer he was to be contented therewith: and good reaſon; for as the Prophet tels vs, there is no want to them that feare him; they want not beautie, riches, pleaſure, nor content; Chriſt is all in all vnto them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The continuance of this Iewell, it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures for euer, hauing the promiſe of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, this of grace the other of glory: when fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb facs="tcp:17653:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> deceiues, and beauty failes, the feare of the Lord endures without change; when all other pleaſures leaue a dampe behind, the feare of the Lord onely makes rich, and hee addes no ſorrow with it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the deſire of the beſt woemen in euery age, ſeeking to attaine it, rather then beautie, riches, foode, or rayment; whoſe actions, are for your imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; let others pin, plait, and paint, ſpend you theſe precious howers in prayer: Let <hi>Martha</hi> bee troubled with many things, take you <hi>Maries</hi> choice, it will bring <hi>Marthaes</hi> gaine without her trouble. Like as <hi>Salomon</hi> asking wiſedome, obtained alſo honour, riches, long life; ſo fals it out with thoſe that feare the Lord, it brings with it all other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries: fauour and beautie may bee without the feare of God: the feare of God not without them: and as it was a chiefe part of wiſedome in <hi>Salomon</hi> to deſire wiſedome: ſo is it a ſpeciall part of holy policie in woemen to chuſe the feare of the Lord,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note> as their chiefeſt ornament: God will adde the reſt: no man euer ſerued the Lord in vaine.</p>
            <p>In the application of this doctrine wee find mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter firſt to informe woemen, what they ſhould moſt earneſtly ſeeke after: if they would be good wiues, and bring a laſting portion with them to their husbands, <hi>The feare of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 6.33.</note> It is the Command of our Sauiour, ſtrengthened by a promiſe: ſeeke firſt the Kingdome of Heauen, and all other things ſhall be added vnto you: this makes woemen moſt louely and onely praiſe-worthy: their preſence highly eſteemed during life: and their memory
<pb facs="tcp:17653:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> honoured after death: this makes woemen ſhine in the darkeſt age; fruitfull in euery good worke, conſcionable in their wayes both toward God and man: obſerue, and you ſhall find how pious ſuch are vnto God, dutifull to their husbands, carefull of their houſhold, teaching Children, guiding ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, giuing good example to both patternes of humility in ſpeech, going, attire.</p>
            <p>They are helpefull, hopefull, euery way beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; I want <hi>Epithetes</hi> to expreſſe their excellency; a woman with this Iewell, is one of the greateſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bleſſings to man on earth; prouided it hang not in the tounge, nor at the eare onely, but in the heart.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion onely here will be; how this Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell may be knowne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> By theſe, or ſome of theſe three things. Firſt, by antecedents, or things going before: Firſt, knowledge of God, his will, preſence, iuſtice, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; of our ſelues, what we haue, wee ſhould not haue, what we want, that we ſhould haue. Secondly, ſorrow of heart, for what we perceiue amiſſe. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, deſire of amendment, which we muſt feele before we can attaine it. Fourthly, enquirie after, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently vſe the meanes, hearing, and reading of the word of God, with prayer and meditation.</p>
            <p>Secondly by ſome properties; which are, firſt to inlighten the vnderſtanding in ſome meaſure accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the capabilitie of the ſubiect. Secondly, to purifie the heart, not from the being, but from the raigne of ſinne. Thirdly, to heate, and enkindle zeale in the affection, for Gods glory. Fourthly,
<pb facs="tcp:17653:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> to direct in the right way to heauen; like as the Load-ſtone turnes the ſinger towards the North; ſoe this feare of God makes women ſtill looke vnto Chriſt, that they may ſafely ſaile, betweene the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous rockes, of doubtfull, and vnlawfull things. Thirdly, by ſome Conſequents as firſt to hate euery ſinne, and foule faſhion of the world, ſo ſoone as knowne. Secondly, to delight in the practice of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere obedience: without partialitie, hypocriſie, formalitie, or temporizing neuteralitie: to be more in deedes then words; to doe more at home, then abroade.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to make conſcience of both theſe, to eſchew euill, and doe good in obedience vnto God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Queſtion.</hi> But how may this Iewell bee at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi> Firſt, by meditation vpon the former particulars: ſecondly, by practice; and that is firſt remotion of all lets and hinderances, with the wiſe Merchant, we muſt part with all wee haue to buy this pearle.</p>
            <p>Secondly reſolution, to doe what euer the Lord commands vs in his word, both for time and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, without diſtinction, pretence, or exception.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to teach men what they ſhould moſt affect and praiſe in woemen; not riches or beautie, though both the gifts of God: Did you know the worth of a vertuous wife, her fidelity, ſedulitie, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie, humilitie, patience, ſweet carriage and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, you would ſeeke her more greedily then any hungry Spaniard doth the Indian gold, or any
<pb facs="tcp:17653:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> amorous wanton, his deceitfull minion: know this further, woemen would not offend ſo much about their faces, did not men offend firſt in exceſſiue prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of their fading beauty.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to ſtirre vp the parents care, by their godly endeauour, to leaue this portion to euery one of their Daughters: you would haue your children doe things praiſe-worthy, then giue them good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, teach them the feare of the Lord; and they ſhall bee praiſed: God hath ſpoken: the preſent ſight of a vertuous face is more delightfull, then gold or laud; the one as vncertaine reſpects the body on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: the other as a laſting Iewell; regardes both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſoule. But alas, the greateſt care in many parents is, to ſowe in their Children the ſeedes of pride, and idlenes, by keeping them in the faſhion for their haire, face, attire, geſture, complement, &amp;c. neglecting the old faſhion, after which God made them; to ſet them vp on high, the churliſh thiſtles daughter, muſt marry with the Cedars ſonne, only for his height; plodding to leaue them rich, though graceleſſe: a greater fault there is in ſome other pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, whoſe indeauour is to diſhearten and hinder their forward children in good courſes; like the Scribes and Phariſees, will neither enter heauen, nor ſuffer thoſe that would. I aduiſe children to honour their parents, becauſe of our precept, but God more, becauſe of many, parents are deare, Chriſt dearer; their loue precious, his ineſtimable, the parents care may adorne the body, this feare of the Lord is the ſoules ornament.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this ſerues to vnuaile the deformed po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie
<pb facs="tcp:17653:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> of ſuch women as want this Iewell; though faire, yet faithleſſe; and may be compared to an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh bogge or quagmire, which appeares greene and ſolid, till it be tried; then opens her mouth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure the paſſenger: ſuch are faire rich women without grace; to looke vnto they are like a bed of downe; to touch, like a bundle of the ſharpeſt thornes: whoſoeuer deales with them, had better grapple with a neſt of ſnakes: their ornaments are all outward, and ſuch as are indeede, the diſgrace of Chriſtianitie, borrowing, poudering, frizeling, and cutting of their haire; naked breaſts, ear-rings, noſe-iewels, with ſtrange fantaſticke faſhions: yet what a gay ſhow doe ſuch make; eſteeming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues no meane perſons, (no more they are not; for they are alwaies in extreames) how haughtie are they, walking with ſtretched-forth neckes, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton eyes, tripping nicely, as they goe? how are they admired by ſimple ones, that know them not? when as there is nothing in them praiſe-worthy; it muſt needs bee folly, fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttery, or both to commend them: if wee giue them the fruit of their hands, and let their owne workes ſpeake for them, what a harueſt muſt they reape? will they not bluſh to heare and ſee pride, idleneſſe, luſt, drunkenneſſe, laid before them as their owne? Oh, conſider this, yee back-ſliding proud wanton, wine-bibbing, loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaking daughters; the fruit of your hand ſhall be giuen you, when nothing can be ſpoken of you but will diſpraiſe you here, and after death; your name and memory ſhall rott away: it is not a bare out-ſide will praiſe you, nor painting that can preſerue you;
<pb facs="tcp:17653:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> your muffes, ruffes, laces, lawnes, perfumes, rings, bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celets, with the reſt of that deceitfull burthen, (a compleatly faſhionable woman in our age, beares a little packe about her) laid aſide, what is left, but a barren carcaſſe, that neuer did, nor is like to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue any good without ſpeedy repentance and reformation.</p>
            <p>Let no vertuous Matrons, be diſcouraged here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, nothing is ſpoken againſt; yea, I haue comfort for them in ſtore: Feare not yee; I know you feare and ſeeke the Lord Ieſus: and what can daunt you? ſhould pouertie? Chriſt is your riches: ſickneſſe? Chriſt is your health; contempt in this world? ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured you are, and ſhall be in heauen, want of a good complexion? alas, it is nothing; and it may be, it is in mercy thoſe that haue it, ſinne more about it, and encreaſe ſinners amongſt men, or of due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, amongſt the partes of the body? mee thinkes a little grace doth abundantly ſupply all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in nature: a woeman that feares God, appeares alwaies moſt amiable and louely; though in bodie neuer ſo deformed: let this Iewell of the ſoule com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort you againſt all other croſſes, though you had nothing elſe in this world, glorie in this, that you know and feare the Lord.</p>
            <p>I may ſtay no longer here: let me exhort you that haue heard, or by any other meanes, ſhall heare what I haue deliuered this day, to affect true prayſe: bee wiues indeed, and truth, like helpfull parts in a liuing body, not in name and ſhew onely like artificiall eyes, which ſupplying the roome, performe no part of the office of an eye: wiues neglecting their
<pb facs="tcp:17653:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> dutie; when they ſhould be helpfull, become hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; are but the ſhadowes of wiues, and were they ſhadowes onely, it were well with thoſe that haue them, if you would haue the reward, doe the worke of good wiues: ſeeke the chiefeſt Iewell, weare the beſt ornament; then know, though fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour be deceitfull, and beautie vanitie; yet a woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that feares the Lord ſhall be praiſed.</p>
            <p>We all ſtand bound to acknowledge this grace in thoſe woemen, on whom God hath beſtowed it; husbands, children, neighbours; yea, the whole Church muſt giue them the fruit of their hands: whence ariſes for our inſtruction this third and laſt concluſion. That it is a neceſſary, no arbitrary acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to giue vertuous women their due commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: beautie is vanitie, and fauour deceitfull; not worthy naming; but a woman that feares the Lord, ſhee ſhall bee praiſed; that is, acknowledged for ſuch, and commended: beſides this precept we find the ſpirit of God hath practiſed it elſe-where: it is ſtoried of <hi>Ruth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth. 3.11.</note> that all the people of the Citie did know her for a vertuous woeman, that is, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge commend, and praiſe her: of <hi>Abigail,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.3.</note> that ſhe was a woman of a good vnderſtanding: in the booke of Kings,<note place="margin">2. Kings 4.9.</note> we find the good Shunamite com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended: and our bleſſed Sauiour himſelfe, enioynes it to bee done of one woman,<note place="margin">Math. 26.13.</note> for a good worke performed by her: whereſoeuer this Goſpell ſhall be preached in the whole world, there alſo ſhall this that this woman hath done, be told, for a memoriall of her. So of <hi>Tabitha</hi> the ſpirit records,<note place="margin">Acts 9.36.</note> that ſhe was full of good workes, and almeſ-deeds which ſhe did.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17653:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Neither is it without Gods guiding prouidence, but by ſpeciall direction, that humane hiſtories, haue beene ſuch faithfull records, of the acts of vertuous woemen (I confeſſe ſome haue impiouſly dipt their pens ouer-deepe in the waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> going to deſcribe the female ſexe, ſo painfully pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing their owne diſgrace,) <hi>Suetonius</hi> makes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Claudia,</hi> who ſeeing her father, riding through the ſtreets of <hi>Rome,</hi> to be pluckt from his triumphant Chariot by the Tribunes, with a maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine boldneſſe freed him from their hands, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him againe in his ſeate, and neuer left till ſhee ſaw him, receiued withall magnificent pompe into the Capitoll. <hi>Solinus</hi> mentions another Romane Lady who when her mother was committed to ſtraight priſon by the <hi>Triumuiri,</hi> there to be ſtarued to death, ſhee nouriſht her with the milke of her owne breſt: <hi>Plinie</hi> tels vs of another who did the like vnto her owne condemned Father. Wee read of <hi>Alceſte,</hi> that died to ſaue the life of her husband <hi>Admetus;</hi> drawing from her owne chaſte breaſt, ſuch, and ſo many ſolid drops of blood, as erected for her ſelfe a liuing monument of honour to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt time; the like inſtance I find in <hi>Iulia,</hi> the wife of <hi>Pompey,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Plutarch:</hi> in <hi>Portia</hi> the wife of <hi>Brutus,</hi> commended to vs by <hi>Valerius Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iminus:</hi> and in <hi>Pompeia Paulina,</hi> the wife of <hi>Seneca:</hi> with many others, whoſe names deſerue to bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen in pillars of Marble, and all to teach vs the neceſſity of this duty.</p>
            <p>Which will further appeare if wee conſider theſe enforcements. Firſt, there are many that haue had
<pb facs="tcp:17653:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> and doe deſerue this praiſe, you haue read or heard (I preſume) of <hi>Rachel,</hi> and the pillar <hi>Iacob</hi> erected in memory of her, of <hi>Deborah. Hannah, Eſter, Iudeth, Marie, Martha, Lydia, Sarah, &amp;c.</hi> whoſe names, and condions, are regiſtred by a neuer-erring Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; to tell vs, God is as wel pleaſed with the gracious actions of good woemen, as with the beſt of any of the ſonnes of men; and that we, as he, ought to giue them their due commendation: who can paſſe ouer in ſilence the renowned names of our two fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Engliſh <hi>Elizabeths,</hi> without admiring the one for valiant doing, the other for patient ſuffering, many calamities (the Lord in mercy, put an end vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them in his time) and prayſing both for their vertues; many others I could name where I liue, and haue liued, who deſerue it, but deſire it not; let their owne workes praiſe them in the gates.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this makes much for Gods glory, whoſe power is moſt ſeene in weakeneſſe, what is praiſe worthy, is the ſpeciall worke of God: their weakeneſſe magnifies his power; when they are praiſed for good workes, hee is glorified.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is a meanes to augment that which is commended in them: vertue increaſes by praiſe, if it be in an humble minde; or elſe indeed it is not vertue. Fourthly, it is a neceſſary part of diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Iuſtice, to giue to euery one their owne, praiſe to whom praiſe belongs. Fiftly, it is beneficiall to all others, as to excite and ſtirre them vp earneſtly, to ſeeke after that Iewell, yea, to ſell all they haue, to buy it, which is ſo highly and generally commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: ſo alſo it will ſerue as a patterne to ſhew them
<pb facs="tcp:17653:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> how they muſt liue, if they would be prayſed; and although none would be praiſed, yet all muſt doe things worthy praiſe. Sixtly, it is comfortable to ſuruiuing friends: by this meanes though death haue depriued you of the preſence of many good and vertuous woemen; yet of the preſence of their vertue and good workes, it cannot: a good name is left ſtill, yea, a freſh memory, which will ſpeake in their praiſe, when they are turned to clay, grace our-liues death; it ſtoopes not to the graue, but wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tes on the ſoule to the throne of glory; beauty and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour moulder into duſt, the feare of the Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures for euer. It cannot be but a great comfort to heare wiſe men, and religious woemen, ſpeake tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in prayſe of our departed friends; to ſee the pens of ſtrangers employed as Gods inſtruments to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh their due praiſe, a reward to them, an example to others.</p>
            <p>In the application of this Leſſon, we find mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of direction, teaching vs, as to practiſe what is here inioyned for the time to come; ſo to be ſorry for former neglects: we may not, we muſt not be ſilent in the praiſe of good woemen: their number is ſmall, the fault may be ours: when goodneſſe is ſlighted or diſeſteemed by moſt, weake woemen ſeeke it not at all: let others be condemned for not ſeeking it when they ſhould; rather then any of vs, for not prayſing it, where it is: But ſtay; are wee not too forward in this point? doe not moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daube the dead with vndeſerued praiſes? too many no doubt: but then the rule ſet downe here is not obſerued: they praiſe them, but doe not giue them
<pb facs="tcp:17653:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> the workes of their owne hands: they rob one to enrich another, take Iewels from the Iſraelites, and giue them to the Egiptians: as in <hi>Rome</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtrumpets haue beene highly extold; ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, thoſe are often prayſed after death, both in funerall Orations and ordinary talke, who neuer yeelded any fruit praiſe-worthy during life: by this fauning ſtile, God is highly diſhonoured, good men and woemen diſcouraged, and the vildeſt wretches countenanced in euill: I ſpeake not this as condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning al thoſe which haue, or do caſt a few flowers vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the coffin of the dead, it may be they ſaw more in them then all others did: but could wiſh men in this kind, where ſin raignes euidently, aboue the feare of God, to be wiſely ſparing for feare of future danger.</p>
            <p>If any demand here how a good woeman may be knowne, that ſo they may praiſe her and giue her the worke of her hands without offence to any? I anſwere; for this end you muſt make vſe both of your eye and eare, a good woeman may be knowne, partly by what you ſee in her, partly by what you heare of her: Firſt, by what you ſee in her, that ſhe be (as farre forch as is poſſible for man to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne) firſt vertuous, inricht with competencie of knowledge, and a good vnderſtanding agreeable to her Sexe: able to diſcerne betweene good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill morally; and accordingly to make choyce, both for ſpeculation and practice; with wiſedome (which conſiſts in ſeeking for) finding out, following and maintaining the truth, according to abilitie, place, and calling; with iuſtice, ready to giue vnto euery one their owne: pietie to God, fidelitie to her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
<pb facs="tcp:17653:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> charitie to the needie, and diligent induſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to her charge in familie: with temperance, a vertue fetching backe all extreames to a mediocritie, and is employed in euery vertuous woman, about theſe particulars eſpecially. Firſt, her wordes, that they be not raſh, haſtie, loud, nor many, eſpecially in the preſence of her husband. Secondly, her plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that ſhe ſeeke not ſo much as is deſired by the vnregenerate part, nor any at all, as the fleſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires it: let that which is reported of <hi>Semiramis, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiphae, Fauſtina, Meſſalina,</hi> with many other filthy woemen amongſt the Gentiles, both Grecians and Romanes,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.26.</note> keepe backe all from ſubmiſſion of their reaſonable part to the ſlauiſh regiment of ſenſe and carnall appetite; thinke not with delight of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety, leſt you deſire it; deſire it not, leſt Sathan offer you meanes to act it; act it not, leaſt after, in ſtead of expected ſatisfaction, it lay you open, to further inuaſion. Thirdly, her dyet, that ſhe be neither care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, curious, or exceſſiue in meate or drinke, for quantitie, nor ouer-much, (the guiſe of drunken Goſſips) for qualitie ouer-daintie, a ſinfull ſauce, wherewith proud <hi>Cleopatra</hi> entertained her familiar gueſt <hi>Marke Anthonie.</hi> Fourthly, about her ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, that ſhe be neither gariſh nor ſluttiſh, that ſhe paſſe not the bounds of her Husbands calling, and abilitie, either in the matter, or manner, ground or faſhion of her attire.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is required ſhe be religious in affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, profeſſion, and conuerſation; that ſhe delight in the hearing of Gods word, obſerue due howers of prayer publique with the Church, eſpecially on
<pb facs="tcp:17653:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Lords day, not ſlighting it at other appointed times; priuate by her ſelfe, and after with her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie, ſo ordering her houſhold buſineſſe, that this dutie may not be omitted, or interrupted through her default: that ſhee loue Gods ſeruants, counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing with her beſt indeauour the beſt things; without this all the reſt are little worth: chuſe no wife, praiſe none choſen, without ſome ſignes of grace, ſome manifeſtation of the power of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is required, ſhe be obedient, humble, chaſte, ſober, diſcreete in her carriage, and outward behauiour: obſerue a woman in her houſe, table, and furniture, for order and dſpoſition of things left to her truſt, in her cloathing, going, laughing, and talking; and you may quickly diſcerne her what ſhe is in theſe as in a glaſſe, the minde is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, formall hypocrites, faile manifeſtly in ſome of theſe, when an honeſt heart keepes a decorum in all.</p>
            <p>Secondly, you may iudge of a woman by what you heare of her; not from euery tongue; ſome inuent to publiſh what may pleaſe their owne, or the itching fancie of an il-willing neighbour; ſome paſſe ſentence raſhly, without Iudgement or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, vpon heare-ſay from others as bad as them ſelues; ſo fame becomes a liar) but from the beſt and moſt iudicious, who are ſo obſeruant of good things, that a gracious woman cannot miſſe a good report, where ere ſhe liues. Feare not, omit not to giue ſuch a one the fruit of her hands, and let her owne workes praiſe her in the gates.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17653:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A ſort of men there haue beene, and are (a vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous broode of degenerating Adamites) who doe ſo baſely deiect woeman-kinde, as to thinke and ſay, nothing they can doe, is praiſe-worthy: ſo their actions, though painfull and pious, neuer come in remembrance to be ſpoken of, or in a cold ſlight, and ſcornefull manner onely: how highly theſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and diſhonour God Almightie, in denying them the worke of their owne handes, and diſeſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that exact part of his workemanſhip. I would they knew: enuying the good they might ſee in them, or fretting at their praiſe.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding this vnnaturall ſpight and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked behauiour of ſome men, in denying women due praiſe, and giuing them the heauy fruit of their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly hands, beating in ſtead of praiſing, who haue their reward: what comfort and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould the conſideration of this Scripture, yeeld to godly, vertuous, and religious woemen; though men ſhould not, yet God you ſee doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect you; hee hath done it, and will continually raiſe vp others to giue you the fruit of your hands: onely remember to doe worthily in <hi>Ephrata,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth. 4.11.</note> and you ſhall be famous in <hi>Bethelem.</hi> You cannot loſe the reward of wel-doing;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note> your labour is not in vaine in the Lord: ſowe nothing you will be aſhamed to receiue;<note place="margin">Gal. 6.7.8, 9, 10.</note> in due ſeaſon you ſhall reape if you faint not: your owne good workes of pietie and charitie done during life (though all things elſe ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire in a ſinfull ſilence) ſhall ſpeake and praiſe you in the gates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the Text hitherto.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17653:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17653:20"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17653:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And now for concluſion, it may bee expected, and is, as it hath beene a commendable cuſtome in this and other Churches (in the pureſt ſeaſon) I ſhould adde ſomething in particular, concerning the occaſion of our meeting; which is to interre the Corps (ere-while containing a vertuous ſoule) of Miſtris <hi>Marie Croſſe:</hi> And were not my purpoſe ſuch, I ſhould be iniurious to her name, vniuſt to her deſert, and firſt of all giue ill example in thwart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my owne Doctrine; which I hope (through Gods grace enabling) I willingly neuer ſhall. It is no arbitrary, but a neceſſary dutie, to giue this good woeman ſome part of her due commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the comfort of the ſhruiming friends, and the encouragement of many vertuous Matrons left behinde.</p>
            <p>To name the Text onely were ſufficient, <hi>Fauour is deceitfull, and beautie vanitie, but a woman that feares the Lord ſhall be prayſed.</hi> You are all perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (I doubt not) ſhe was a woman that feared the Lord heartily, and therefore muſt be praiſed: deale iuſtly with her; giue her the fruit of her hands, and let vs permit her owne good workes to ſpeake for her, and praiſe her in the gates. For my owne part, as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> anſwered the Scribes and Rulers,<note place="margin">Acts 4.20.</note> I cannot but ſpeake of her the good things I haue heard and ſeene; willing and reſoluing, as <hi>Ierome</hi> concerning <hi>Marcella,</hi> to praiſe nothing in her, but what was truely made her owne by the gift of God: What <hi>Boaz</hi> ſaid of <hi>Ruth,</hi> in her is fitly verified. You haue all long knowne her to bee a vertuous Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, euery way commendable, whether wee
<pb facs="tcp:17653:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> conſider her as a Woeman, as a Wife, or as a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>As a Woman; (with her Birth and Parentage I was neuer acquainted) this I know, what the Scripture ſpeakes of <hi>Abigail,</hi> applies it ſelfe vnto her; ſhe was a Woman of a good vnderſtanding; wiſe, iuſt, ſober, chaſte, louing, diſcreete in all her actions, temperate in wordes, in pleaſure, diet, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell; from faults I exempt her not; ſinnes ſhee had, inward corruptions, whereof ſhe would often complaine with teares, elſe we nor ſhee had beene here to day.</p>
            <p>As a Wife; you haue beene eye-witneſſes of her dutifull obedience, ſubmiſſiue and reuerend beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour; indued ſhe was with a great meaſure of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, carefull to content her Husband, gouerne her houſe, and to bring vp her children in the feare of the Lord, reading to them, examining of them in the grounds, and principles of Religion, (the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of euery good woman, according to abilitie) ſo ſpending ſpare houres, when others were at the Goſſips play; neither was it labour in vaine, Gods bleſſing in her Children was one of her chiefeſt comforts to her dying day.</p>
            <p>As a Chriſtian? ſhe hath beene an ancient Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, a profeſſour of Religion in the power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and a practitioner of pietie in truth and ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; this was her onely ioy, comfort elſe, being wondrous ſickly, ſhee had but little in this world; ornaments, with other feminine toyes ſhee eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med none; in compariſon of this Iewell: much good I haue obſerued in her my ſelfe, but haue
<pb facs="tcp:17653:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> heard much more, admiring the truth and power of God, that ſome ſhould praiſe her for her pious deuotion and religious behauiour, who yet were neuer guiltie of any good. Three things eſpecially are reported of her by faithfull witneſſes: Firſt, that ſhe ſpent conſtantly ſome part of euery day in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and meditating on the word of God, and that ſhee read ouer the Bible this laſt halfe yeare before her death; as if her commiſſion had run thus; read my will once more, and then come home: a ſhame to ſuch who haue liued in health many whole yeares, and hitherto haue neuer read it ouer: many vſe their booke a little on the Lords day, turne to places, cited, as if they would note them for future meditation: but returning home, the booke is laid vp in a ſpare roome, nere troubled more till ſome ſeruant come to ſhake off the duſt, that it be fit for publike vſe in the eye of the Church; with ſuch formalities God is not pleaſed: if ſhe be bleſſed for delighting in the law of God day and night, as ſhe did; what are they?</p>
            <p>Secondly, that ſhe would not ſleepe on the Lords day; no, not in the greateſt extremitie of her laſt ſickneſſe, notwithſtanding that her weake body was chiefly ſuſtained by ſleepe, and her friends and Children would often perſwade to it, vrging Gods gracious acceptance of the will for the deed, where abilitie was wanting to actuate good deſires: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, in the iudgement of the ſtricteſt Diuines, it is very lawfull and tolerable, yet in the exuberance of her zeale, her anſwere ſtill was thus, or to this effect: no ſhe would not yeeld that day to ſleepe, it was the Lords day, the Soules market-day: if I
<pb facs="tcp:17653:22"/> loſe this day, what ſhall the Soule feede on all the weeke after? How ſhould I anſwere it if my Lord ſhould come and call to take mee hence, finding mee this day ſleeping? I will not doe it; can I not watch one houre? the health of body I both reſpect and deſire, preferring ſtill the welfare of the ſoule, and though I cannot ſpend it as I would, being Gods priſoner, yet my endeauour ſhall not be wanting in heart and minde, to ioyne with the publike aſſembly, and ſuch indeed her manner was to ſpend the whole day when ſhe could not goe to Church (her lingring diſeaſe did ſtay her long and often) in prayer, reading and meditation: a ſhame to ſuch among vs, that prophanely miſ-ſpend the Lords day, ſleeping all the morning ſecurely, till the Bell cals them: as if putting on of our beſt cloathes, and running away, were all, nothing elſe required, when ſome preparation is as neceſſary as the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: he ſhall bring home but little good, that goes to market without money in his purſe; greater ſhame to ſuch as come to ſleepe in the Church: her zeale would not permit her to ſleepe in great weakeneſſe, on her bed alone, where none could be offended. Gods awfull preſence cannot keepe you from ſleeping in health, in Gods houſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a multitude, where many are offended thereby: if her vigilancie bee to be admired, take heede leaſt Iudgement finde you napping.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that ſhe obſerued conſtant houres eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day for priuate prayer on her knees; euen when for very weakeneſſe ſhee could not riſe againe, till ſome came in to helpe her vp. Oh happy Soldier!
<pb facs="tcp:17653:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> thy warre is ended, victory wonne, and the crowne obtained; ſing deare Saint the ſongs of Zion: thy teares are waſht away, enioy thy reſt.</p>
            <p>I could delightfully ſtay here to admire this free priſoner, in her heauenly conuerſation, till the houre of her deſired diſſolution. To behold in a weake, leane, dying body, true beautie and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the picture of pietie in this ſpirituall anatomie: how welcome is weakeneſſe, when accompanied with ſuch ſtrength of grace? but me thinkes I ſee already your eyes full, and the glaſſe emptie, I may not ſtay. One thing I would requeſt of her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and Children, before I leaue, and that is, they would make knowne vnto the world, their loue, dutie, and reſpect vnto her, by imitation of her in pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie, humilitie, ſobrietie, frugalitie and loue towards Gods Children, follow her in grace, you ſhall follow her to glory, and let this be ingrauen on her Tombe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>As ſhe liued, in the feare of the Lord.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>So ſhee dyed, in the feare of the Lord.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Laſtly, to conclude in a word to you all my right dearely beloued, if you like this that you haue heard to day; and deſire ſo much might be ſpoken of you after death, goe home, and do likewiſe: ſell all you haue for this Iewell; ſhake off your deareſt ſinne; liue in the <hi>feare of the Lord,</hi> you ſhall dye in his fauour, the fruit of your hands ſhall bee giuen you, and your owne workes ſhall praiſe you in the gates.</p>
            <closer>Soli Deo Gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
